- There was nothing
particularly unusual about that 7, 30th, 1945.
Subways, railroad terminals,
and ferry boats is for office bound millions.
Women went about their
housework and later their days shopping.
Part of this normal life was newspaper. Taken as a matter of course, by everyone.
So regular and complete a
part of normal everyday living that finding newspapers on the news then, buying them morning and night
was taken pretty much for granted.
Never a thought of the rumbling
presses that produced them. Completely oblivious to the
vast transportation system that placed them so conveniently
on 14 thousand, strategically located news stands through out the city.
No reason to contemplate what
life without newspapers would mean.
Until it suddenly, and with
little warning, STRIKE!
1700 delivery men ceased work.
newspaper trucks stopped rolling. News stands formerly piled
high with eight daily New York newspapers where
devoid of newspapers, devoid of customers.
Barron as a desert waste.
With the lone exception of PM, news stands were as bare as
mother Hubbard's cupboard.
13 million metropolitan new
Yorkers, deprived of their daily newspaper fair.
And this at a time when
great events were in the making the world over.
President Truman was on his way to a meeting of the big three.
Japanese cities were
being laid waste by B-29s. Thousands of American boys were
returning home from European battlefields.
Now newspapers were more than a habit, more than a convenience.
They were a necessity. Here then was the time
of all times for radio, the psychological moment.
For years, the point has been argued, discussion has raised pro and
con, will radio eventually supplant newspaper?
Isn't it easier to turn a switch,
than to read an editorial?
Yes, for radio, here was
a heaven sent opportunity.
Reluctant to profit by adversity. Hesitant to capitalize misfortune.
Radio nevertheless had a job to do. A public service to perform.
And radio rose, nobly, to the occasion. Newscasters and commentators
labored long and hard.
Radio news programs were
substantially increased. Many newspapers either started
or increased their regular news radio roundup.
The times was on the air
every hour, on the hour. The Herald Tribune had
a regular news period.
The news doubled its schedule. Went on the air 48 times a day.
At almost any hour, day or night. The public could flip a
dial, and hear a newscast.
Certainly if news by a radio, could satisfy the news hungry public.
Radio was giving it every chance.
But something was lacking, an appetizer is a poor
substitute for a full meal.
A starving man languages
on a Hollywood diet. Radio was apparently not the right answer.
Newspaper readers, telephone then, and discovered that despite
tickets newspapers were still being published every day.
Learned, they could have obtain copies by going directly to the newspaper plant.
Here is the Herald Tribune
plant on the first day of the strike.
Showing the truck loading
platform used to sell papers in the emergency.
The first day of the strike, Herald Tribune circulation
plummeted to 15,000.
But as more and more loyal
Tribune readers learned they could buy the paper at the plant, they went to the Herald Tribune
in ever increasing numbers.
On the last day of the strike, the Herald Tribune sold 65,000 copies.
By far, the greater
portion of them in direct, over the counter sale, to Tribune readers, who had taken the time and
trouble, to come far out of their way to get a copy
of their favorite morning newspaper.
This represents as surprisingly
high percentage of Tribune circulation achieved under
extremely difficult condition.
Meanwhile, a flood of Tribune
readers phoned the paper. - Please give me more
information on the change in red point value.
- Is it true that president
Truman is out of the country? - On what troop ship is
my husband returning home?
Now let's move to the journal American. Here is a newspaper plant, so disadvantageously located
for the general public, that the paper maintains
frequent bus service for its own employee, to a nearby
transportation center.
The sirens of east river shipping
convoys provide a musical background for the roar of the presses.
Despite its inaccessible location journal, American readers traveled, to the plant on south street, in droves.
Circulation on the first day
of the strike drops to 4,000. But by the end of the strike, daily sales figures climbed to 25,000.
Mirror fans lined up at the Mirror plant in mounting crescendo.
Daily sales figures are unavailable, but through teaming rain and
glazing heat, Mirror readers made the trip to the plant, stood in line, made their purchase.
The New York Sun, here was new
York's longest picket line. It is impossible to show
the full effect of the Sun readership line, because
the paper was sold inside the building.
Sun readers entered
the marble lobby of the building, shown in the center, made their purchase inside,
and emerged through the door, at the left.
When sales got too heavy
for the emergency office, boxes were set up in the Marble foyer, to serve as temporary news stands.
Then during rush hours, the place looked like grand station.
Circulation climbed from a low of 23,000, on the first day of the
strike, to a high of 78,000 on the last day.
The New York world Telegraph.
This plant is located downtown, near the New Jersey commuting terminal.
The entrance where papers were
sold is situated on a narrow side street, in deep shadow, untouched by the rays
of the afternoon sun.
This made it impossible
to take color pictures. There was nothing shadowy, however, about the long lines of
world telegram readers.
Who came from near and far. Readers made the trip to
the World Telegram Plant, all the way from New Haven, Connecticut, from the far corner of long island.
Lines five blocks long
were a daily occurrence. Thousands filed slowly into
the telegram building, and emerged, triumphantly, with their favorite afternoon newspaper.
Circulation rose from 15,000, on the first day of the strike, to 50,000 on the last day.
The New York Times, because
of its Times Square location, and because it is a morning paper, the largest Time's crowd during
weekdays occurred at night, and are not shown here.
Blocks adjacent to the Times,
were frequently choked with readers for a couple of hours
around theater closing time.
A New Jersey resident bought
five copies of the paper, to auction off at a Red Cross meeting.
When the copies of the Times
has got as far as Asbury park, New Jersey, although
well-read by train passengers, they were sold for a
dollar a copy of current.
50 cents if a day old,
a news stand manager at Little Silver, New Jersey, was offered a dollar for a day old Time, but refused to sell because
he wanted to read it himself.
Times' daily circulation rose from 38,000, on the first day of
the strike, to 210,000,
the final day.
The New York News. For
22 hours out of every 24, News readers poured in and
out of the News building, two to four abreast, from
six o'clock in the morning to 4 am the next morning.
Lines began forming in the
afternoon about five o'clock. Stood for 3 hours, to await
the first edition at 8:15 PM.
The longest line occurred on
a Saturday night, to buy the Sunday news.
This line, 17 blocks
long, snaked its way along Third avenue, back and
forth on cross streets, to 32nd street.
City police went through
the subways at 34th street, warning passengers bound
for the news building, to get off of there, to join the line, instead of going on up to 42nd Street.
Assistant Chief Inspector, John de Martino of the New York
City Police Department said, - This was the biggest lineup
crowd in my experience at average 30,000 per hours.
People stood in line for 2
hours, before reaching the counter.
42nd street grew accustomed
to a daily ritual. Passing trolley cars were
parked, while motormen and passengers got off to buy the paper.
Taxis, private cars, the
street, and adjacent blocks were packed throughout each evening, with vehicles, while
passengers and drivers bought the news.
One of the picketers, after
shedding his sign, nightly went inside to buy his paper.
From 37,000 over the counter sales, on the first day of the strike, sales zoom to 915,000 on the last day.
Of which 584,000 sales,
were made over the counter to individuals in the lines you see.
Happily, however, even laborer strike, has its lighter moment.
By courtesy of Movietone News, Mayor F. H. LaGuardia reads the comic.
[Preppy Marching Music]
[Unintelligible] - Now here in full picture
is the laundry Wagon with the yellow laundry writing.
And what brought back
the driver, you know, he uh was very calmly, sitting
down with his back toward the back of the wagon, eating his lunch.
And our little friend at the
hub, uh what was her name? I'll have it in minute,
she's inside with the money.
As she said, "when are you
going to let me out of here?" He said, "[Unintelligible]" He said, "Easy sister, easy." And then the next picture, and we hear the sound
from inside the wagon.
Open the door, and Wet
Wash says, "I let you off, when you decided to give me
a better cut of that dough."
From the inside. And we see the inside.
"Now, I offered $1,000.
What do you think I am?" "This is my money!" And if you remember, she stopped stripping them, tearing up the laundry, and
she had all of the money in bills, in the pillows. That we
hear wet wash, "Listen baby," "I know you're a maid at bamboozles," "I saw you there last week," "And I know that something
funny about that dough." "Now when we get it,
it's going to be 50/50!"
"Okay? Then maybe you like some more," "of your laundry, torn
to pieces, RIIIIIIIIP!" She's ripping the lingerie there, delicate piece of
lingerie, and he looks in, "Ye Gods, I lose my job over there." "Stop, you win! I'll
settle for five grand!", now, get this picture, Here was wet wash, the doors
of the laundry wagon are open, and he's leaning with his back toward, the wagon.
And he's counting his money. Two, three, 4,000!
Now he's getting into the
hundreds 600, 700, 800, and the picture shows, a hand, affectless,
specking out.
She's got hold of that iron pot. Remember the iron pot
took from the [Unknown], gardeners flat, to put the money in, and "CRASH!" She cracked it on his head.
knocked out.
Hey children, what does it all mean?
It means that dirty money,
never brings any luck.
- Thus New York learn
that as the newspapers could not to go to the public.
The public would come to the paper. During the 17 days of the strike, the public came to the various plants, bought a total of 10 million, 628 thousand newspaper,
trouble inconvenience.
This was the price paid each
day for New York newspapers, by long lines of people in rain and sun,
standing for hours on hard concrete, risking bodily harm by
cutting through picket lines, impervious to shouted
warnings of tickets in a city, heavily unionized.
Men, women, and children
in all walks of life, giving up a summer evening
of pleasure or relaxation.
Going without lunch or
postponing dinner for hours. Coming for miles and oven warm subways, to stand for a long period, in halting, or slow moving files.
Patient, perspiring, persistent. All for a few penny purchase.
Such is the miracle of
journalism, and such as the significance of newspapers
to their reader, newspapers, which can be read and re-read.
Newspapers in which the public can read all about it, in their own time, at their own convenience.
And thus, was New York's sigh of relief, When the strike finally was
ended, when, within the hour, the trucks were rolling, and New York life returned to normal.
Once again, dramatic proof has been given
that no other medium can take the place of newspapers in
the lives of the people.
And the fundamental reason,
why newspapers are held in such high regard by the American
public, lies in that long cherished bull mark of liberty- Freedom, of the press!